<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: business | Swanand Pagnis]]></title>
  <link href="http://info.pagnis.in/blog/categories/business/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://info.pagnis.in/"/>
  <updated>2020-10-14T13:15:08+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://info.pagnis.in/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Swanand Pagnis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notes from 'Blind Spots of the Developer Entrepreneur']]></title>
    <link href="http://info.pagnis.in/blog/2020/07/11/notes-from-developer-entrepreneur-talk/"/>
    <updated>2020-07-11T22:45:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://info.pagnis.in/blog/2020/07/11/notes-from-developer-entrepreneur-talk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the 2017 MicroConf, <a href="https://twitter.com/r00k">Ben Orenstein</a> spoke about &ldquo;The Blind Spots of the Developer Entrepreneur&rdquo;. It was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n078RDNz6jY">a talk packed with insights</a> and actionable advice for the developer-entrepreneur.</p>

<p>The target audience for the talk is someone who wants to start their own business but hasn&rsquo;t begun. But even if you don&rsquo;t fit this criterion, it still offers value in the methodical approach it prescribes.</p>

<p>Personally, the talk resonated with me and renewed my interest in wanting to teach and building a viable business out of teaching.</p>

<p>Here are my notes from the talk. The points are his, the phrasing is mine.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Part 1: First steps 👣</h2>

<p>The talk is prescriptive. Why? Because when you are starting, you need someone to give you specific instructions.</p>

<p>Progress over perfection. Move that needle.</p>

<p>Ben used an apt analogy of cooking: It would help a great deal if you had recipes when you begin. But you evolve into experimentation only after you cross an expertise threshold.</p>

<p>He also shared his journey as a maker where he started teaching Vim to other developers, a topic he was passionate about. This journey ended up creating a well-loved platform that came to be known as &ldquo;Upcase&rdquo; by ThoughtBought.</p>

<p>He&rsquo;s been there and done that.</p>

<p>There are 2 phases to the beginner&rsquo;s journey.</p>

<h3>Phase 1: Teach 🎓</h3>

<p>The first big question: <strong>What do I teach?</strong></p>

<p><em>What would&rsquo;ve saved you agony if you knew it when you were working on something?</em></p>

<p><em>What are people asking you about?</em> This prompt is useful since it indicates that you already evoke some trust in others.</p>

<p><em>What are some things you spend much time on or enjoy doing that other people find annoying?</em> Ben gave an anecdotal example of his friend, who <em>loved</em> spending time on invoices and timesheets and chose his first product from this habit: invoicing for freelancers. A much-dreaded task for a vast majority of freelancers.</p>

<p>The second big question: <strong>How do I teach?</strong></p>

<p>Start small, personal, and free.</p>

<ul>
<li>Teach co-workers something related to their everyday work</li>
<li>Give lightning talks at conferences and meetups &mdash; they&rsquo;re an excellent avenue for packing insights into one short, concise session.</li>
<li>An informal Hangouts/Zoom session</li>
</ul>


<p>When you teach, don&rsquo;t just teach, interact. 🗣️</p>

<ul>
<li>Ask people about themselves</li>
<li>Where they work</li>
<li>What excited them about attending this session</li>
<li>What was the best thing they learned</li>
<li>What were the problems</li>
</ul>


<p>These questions and their answers reveal astonishing details about your teachings. You can use those to refine and get better. <em>Get better.</em></p>

<p>As you start teaching, and people start learning from you, you need a way to keep in touch &mdash; collect their emails. You don&rsquo;t have to start a newsletter right away, find a way to inform them of your new content.</p>

<h3>Phase 2: Pre-sell an info product</h3>

<p><strong>Goal: Sell <em>one</em> copy to <em>one</em> stranger.</strong> 🤝</p>

<p>Never start with a SaaS unless you have research to prove the merit; they&rsquo;re much harder to sell.</p>

<p>Start with an info product. A guide. A book. Tutorials.</p>

<p><em>Write one chapter through a process of complete immersion.</em></p>

<p>Take 4-5 days off from your schedule. Focus heavily &mdash; ignore everything else you can ignore. Don&rsquo;t write the introduction or pitch; write a meaty chapter. Go down the trenches and write one of the book&rsquo;s central chapters. And write the table of contents.</p>

<p>Tell them what you&rsquo;re going to tell them. 🎙️</p>

<p>Create a sales page on Leanpub or Gumroad or a similar service. Do not attempt to write code for this sales page. Nope. Have a page ready where people can pay you money and buy your book. Before. You. Complete. It.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t wait for inspiration. It will come in leaps and bounds when you find success. Even micro-success brings inspiration.</p>

<p>Ben alludes to a survey he did at the conference, where it turned out that about 50% of the attendees had $0 revenue because they hadn&rsquo;t started. And about 50% of the attendees felt inspired, and the rest didn&rsquo;t.</p>

<p>And there was substantial overlap with those who did not yet feel inspired and those who had not started.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t wait for inspiration. Put in the work.</p>

<p>Get started &ndash;> Small success &ndash;> Inspiration &ndash;> More work &ndash;> More success</p>

<p>Ben mentioned the thrill he felt when he put up a $9 video about getting better at Vim, and strangers bought it. 💰</p>

<p>Recommended reading: <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1319.The_War_of_Art">The War of Art</a></p>

<h2>Part 2: Ben&rsquo;s Ten Best Tactics</h2>

<p>We have a Ben 10 here.</p>

<p>These don&rsquo;t necessarily apply to beginners or info products. They are appropriate for all digital businesses.</p>

<p><strong> 1️⃣ </strong> Create a recurring reminder to run a pricing test every six months.</p>

<p>Raise your rates. Hide your lowest pricing tier.</p>

<p>There are numerous examples of people doubling and tripling their prices, and still growing.</p>

<p><strong> 2️⃣ </strong> Create an email course. Drip it over 4-5 days. Make it a good, tight content based on genuine value. Remember the &ldquo;what to teach&rdquo; lessons.</p>

<p><strong> 3️⃣ </strong> Integrate and partner with other businesses and products &mdash; a potent formula for creating win-win situations.</p>

<p>Here, Ben shared two examples:</p>

<ul>
<li>A Zapier integration they did, which led to Zapier covering them in a blog post, which in turn led to a massive uptick in customers</li>
<li>He struck a partnership with a competing product with a slightly different niche, leading to an additional $100k revenue for both of them in a span of weeks.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong> 4️⃣ </strong> Sell annual plans. There are a lot of nifty patterns around yearly billing. The reason they work is that they&rsquo;re mutually beneficial.</p>

<p><strong> 5️⃣ </strong> Put faces near things you want people to click. Humans beings are drawn to faces by nature.</p>

<p>Think CTAs, subscribe buttons. Put faces.</p>

<p><strong> 6️⃣ </strong> Try a diving-save. Reach out personally to someone who churned and make an offer that&rsquo;s well worth it. Figure out why someone is canceling and use that to offer some value around it. e.g., you get a cancellation because the student does not have time to work through. Offer them a discounted annual pack so that they have additional time.</p>

<p><strong> 7️⃣ </strong> Start a podcast. A great way to get industry-famous people to talk about you. A great way to get traffic and attention. Podcasts have a vast audience. Utilize it.</p>

<p><strong> 8️⃣ </strong> Manually onboard customers. Yes, for real. Get on a screen sharing call with them and ask them to walk you through as they sign up and start using your service.</p>

<p>It will open up your blindspots and delight you. Or make you cry. Improvements either way!</p>

<p><strong> 9️⃣ </strong> Double down on things that work. You might feel the need to be experimentative or creative, but instead, focus on things that work. It works.</p>

<p><strong> 🔟 </strong> Ask for help.</p>

<p>Ask successful people in the same industry. You will be surprised how willing people are to help. As a corollary, be prepared to help others.</p>

<p><strong>Fin.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
